Jacob Badger

(928) 242-9353 • jcbadger@utexas.edu • users.oden.utexas.edu/~jbadger

Objective

First-year Ph.D. student pursuing a multi-disciplinary degree in Computational Science, Engineering, and Mathematics (CSEM). Passionate problem solver and researcher. Strong technical, interpersonal, and presentation skills. Particularly interested in predictive modeling, and high-order finite element methods.

Education

Academics

University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

Ph.D. in Computational Science, Engineering, and Mathematics (CSEM)

2019-present

CSEM Fellow

Brigham Young University

Provo, UT

BS in Mechanical Engineering and Mathematics (double major)

2015-2019

GPA: 3.95/4.0

- GRE: 170 V, 170 Q (perfect scores)

Notable Projects....

BYU Mars Rover: Autonomous Navigation

Designed and implemented software for autonomous navigation and obstacle avoidance using LIDAR and stereo-camera sensors. Used fuzzy-logic to classify obstacles, potential fields to avoid obstacles, and a neural net to recognize target objects (tennis balls). Implemented in Python/ROS, with limited C++.

Experience

Graduate Research Assistant

University of Texas at Austin

Dr. Leszek Demkowicz

July 2018 - March 2019

- Developed a distributed multigrid preconditioned conjugate gradient solver for hp-adaptive DPG methods
- Developed sum factorization algorithms for fast integration of DPG matrices on prismatic elements

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Brigham Young University

Dr. Larry Howell, Dr. Vianey Villamizar, Dr. Brent Webb

Nov. 2016 - May 2019

- Developed novel equations and algorithms for identifying "natural" curved fold configurations
- Derived and implemented novel high-order local absorbing boundary conditions for acoustic scattering
- Implemented novel SLW radiative heat transfer models in comprehensive combustion models

Teaching Assistant

Brigham Young University

ME 505—Applied Engineering Math

Sept. 2018 - Dec. 2018

Helped students understand PDE solution methods including eigenfunction expansions and integral transforms

Religious Mission

Buenos Aires, Argentina

LDS Church

Aug. 2013 - Aug. 2015

Learned Spanish and worked with people from diverse cultures in humanitarian and missionary efforts

Technical and Personal Skills

- Programming Languages: C++/C, Fortran, MATLAB, Python, Mathematica, HTML/CSS
- Software: Matlab (Advanced), Solidworks (Advanced), Fluent (Advanced), ANSYS (Intermediate)
- Communication: Spanish (Advanced).
- Other: Skilled problem solver, quick learner, relentless.

Publications, Presentations, and Grants

Journal Articles.....

- **J.C. Badger**, S. Henneking, and L. Demkowicz, 2019. "Fast integration of DPG matricies based on sumfactorization." *Oden Institute Report*, 19-15.
- J.C. Badger, T.G. Nelson, R.J. Lang, D.M. Halverson, and L.L. Howell, 2018. "Normalized Coordinate Equations and Energy Method for Predicting Natural Curved-Fold Configurations." *Journal of Applied Mechanics*, 86(7), p.071006.
- **J.C. Badger**, V.P. Solovjov, and B.W. Webb, (in press). "An Exploration of Advanced SLW Modeling Approaches in Comprehensive Combustion Predictions." *Combustion Science and Technology*.
- **J.C. Badger**, S. Acosta, and V. Villamizar, (2019). "High-order local ABC and scaling for multiple acoustic scattering." *Manuscript in preparation*.
- D.L. Corey, **J.C. Badger**, and S. Lauzon, 2018. "Spirals, Triangles, and Tie-dyed T-shirts." *The College Mathematics Journal.* **50**(4), pp. 250-259.

Conference Presentations

- V. Villamizar, J.C. Badger, T. Khajah, and S. Acosta, 2019. "High Order Farfield Expansion ABC coupled with IGA and Finite Differences Applied to Acoustic Multiple Scattering." In 14th International Conference on Mathematical and Numerical Aspects of Wave Propagation (WAVES 2019), Vienna, Austria, 25-30 August 2019.
- V. Villamizar, T. Khajah, J.C. Badger, and S. Acosta, 2019. "High Order Methods for Multiple Scattering Combining Isogeometric Analysis with Farfield Expansion ABC." In 15th U S National Congress on Computational Mechanics (USACM 2019), Austin, 28-31 July 2019.
- **J.C. Badger**, V.P. Solovjov, and B.W. Webb, 2019. "An Exploration of Advanced SLW Modeling Approaches in Comprehensive Combustion Predictions." In *11th Mediterranean Combustion Science meeting* (MCS11), Tenerife, Spain, 16-20 June 2019.
- J.C. Badger, T.G. Nelson, R.J. Lang, and L.L. Howell, 2018. "Explaining Curved-Fold Behavior through Normalized Coordinate Equations and Energy Methods." In 7th International Meeting on Origami, Science, Mathematics and Education (70SME), Oxford, UK, 5-7 September 2018.

Grants

J.C. Badger, and L.L. Howell, "Single Degree-of-Freedom Rigidly Foldable Origami Flashers Based on Curved-Fold Models." BYU ORCA grant, 2016.